Meeting and admitting everybody just.
I'll take a second, All right, OK.
Everybody who was just in the lobby
should be in now and the meeting started,
so we should be good to go.
Let me just say a few words.
Good morning, everyone.
My name is Jorge Gonzalez,
the medical psilocybin program manager.
Good morning and thank you for being here.
We will start in just a minute,
but I just want to make sure that
everyone remembers that this meeting is
being recorded.
So Please remember to keep language
appropriate as the recordings are made
public on the Advisory Board website.
So we'll get those up.
We're having a little delay if you had
questions and look back at our other
minutes and videos because marketing is
getting a little backlog.
So because they have to do it for the
whole Department of Health and so they've
been reviewing a lot of videos and other
things as well.
So those videos will be posted in time,
but in the meantime we are getting the
all the chairpersons documents and are
the minutes posted in in in the meantime.
So those will be up there even a little
bit sooner.
So with that, Ian, go right ahead.
Good morning everyone.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Ian Dunn,
I'm the Chair of the Patient
Qualification and Safety Committee.
I do call this meeting to order at 9:05
AM on April 13th.
I'm really glad you guys could be here.
So this is just continuation on our
discussion from last meeting where we
were working on preparation and the,
you know, mechanics behind that.
We were also discussing the referral
process,
how they get entered into the system and
how they begin their treatment.
So we've provided some clarifying
definitions,
trying to adhere as closely as possible
to what the committee had brought up.
And so we'll be discussing that document
today.
What we changed was clarifying what the
different clinical roles are in order to,
you know,
make sure we had a basis of understanding
for what each person was doing.
I think that's very important in the
preparation session.
And as we get to integration and
administration,
I think it'll be important as well.
So I do want to welcome everyone.
So just a quick reminder,
the purpose of committees is to expand
community input and allow people who have
perceived conflicts of interest to who
may not serve on the board to participate.
It allows it supports the board by
incorporating subject matter expertise
and increasing participation in program
development.
I will now allow anyone who would like to
participate to introduce themselves,
their name, their area of expertise,
and their perspective or interests
related to dosage,
administration and clinical practice.
I'll turn over to Johnny to call anyone
who has hands.
All right.
And if you'd like to make a comment,
you can raise your hand in teams by
selecting the icon with a hand at the top
that says raise.
It varies exactly where it is in the top
banner on right or left for different
people's systems,
but should be a hand that says raise.
Also if you want to put anything in the
chat as well then that will be reflected
in the meeting and looks like first hand
up.
We've got Hannah, Rose and Hannah.
I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when ready.
Hi, good morning.
My name is Hannah Rose.
I am here in Silver City, NM,
BSW student at Western New Mexico for
social work and 1st generation Kurandara
and happy to be here.
Nice to see you all this morning.
Awesome.
Thanks Hannah.
And next, we've got Gregory Evans.
And Gregory, I have enabled your mic.
Good morning.
My name is Gregory Evans.
I'm an independent researcher and a home
psychologist with no affiliations.
I'm a Santa Fe resident,
and my intention is to support the
program's development through committee
recommendations aligned with emerging
research and best practices.
Awesome.
Thanks, Gregory.
And next we have Lisa Johnson.
Lisa, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when ready.
My name is Lisa Johnson.
I'm a marriage and family therapist and
private practice in Albuquerque and I'm
currently taking courses at the
Southwestern College for the
certification for psilocybin practice and
I'm interested in participating in the
process of making sure this that we have
some quality care in New Mexico for the
people who need it.
Awesome.
Thank you Lisa.
And next we've got James Brown and James,
I have enabled your mic.
Morning everyone, and Ian James Brown,
doctor pharmacy here in New Mexico,
psychedelic facilitator,
trained veteran representing 5° N Healing
Foundation.
Love to be here.
Looking forward to this meeting today.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, James.
And next we've got Denali Wilson.
And Denali, your mic is in the name.
Morning everybody.
My name is Denali Wilson.
I'm the director of strategic support for
the Healing Advocacy Fund,
which is a nonprofit that supports state
regulated access to psychedelic healing
with the focus on access and equity.
And yeah, happy to contribute.
I'm going to try and focus today.
I have to jump a little bit early,
but we'll try and provide some thoughts
for the committee to consider in terms of
healthcare integration and the ways that
we talk about referral that might have
implications for coverage.
Awesome.
Thanks, Denali.
And next we've got Kate Hawk and your mic
is enabled.
Good morning, everyone.
I'm Kate Hawk in Santa Fe.
I'm a psychedelic grandmother,
been a MAPS member since the 1980s,
trauma therapist for about that long and
done, gosh, done training,
harm reduction of Burning Man,
all kinds of involvement for a lot of
years.
So I'm here as a person who is not
licensed.
I will add, I've done MAPS training,
Colorado natural Medicine facilitator and
all kinds of other things.
Got a master's in counseling,
but I'm not licensed.
So really interested in how this whole
system can come together and use all of
the resources that we have.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Thank you, Kate.
And next,
we've got Gina Nepal and I have enabled
your mic.
You can unmute when ready.
And as a reminder,
there is a icon that says mic up at the
top.
And if it's greyed out or anything,
if there is a down arrow next to it,
you might want to select that and make
sure that the correct mic for your
computer is selected there.
If you're not able to do either of those.
Also,
dropping off the meeting and then
rejoining sometimes fixes that issue as
well.
So it looks like possibly in the meantime
you're having issues.
You can also drop anything in the chat if
you want.
But oh, sorry,
I'm going to go to the next person here
if you want to drop off the call and
rejoin.
So we're going to go to Sam Wolf.
Sam, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Good morning, Sam Wolf.
I'm an attorney in Santa Fe,
interested in seeing how the process
develops.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Thanks, Sam.
And next we've got Chris Peskowski.
And Chris, your mic is enabled.
Good morning, everybody here.
Chris Miskowski here finds your board
member, veteran hero parts investment.
Awesome.
Thanks, Chris.
And then looks like glassed up,
we've got Asher.
And Asher, I have enabled your mic.
You can unmute when you're ready.
All right,
looks like Asher might be having some
issues as well.
If you want to drop any introduction in
the chat, you're welcome to do so.
You can also rejoin.
And with that,
I'm going to hand it back to Ian and we
can get going.
All righty, and thank you so much,
all of you for being here and
participating.
So first,
let's go ahead and pull up the clinical
roles document.
So initially we're going to go over the
clinical roles.
We it's to try to follow what James Brown
was suggesting in our last meeting,
which was to separate out the person who
is just passing them to the program and
the person that's defining medical
appropriateness in order to expand who
can be a clinician.
So let us begin.
I went ahead and posted it in the chat as
well.
So this would define a referring
clinician as a licensed clinician acting
within their scope of practice who
possesses diagnostic authority.
They would be responsible for identifying
potential candidates based on qualifying
conditions,
provide referral into the program,
share relevant and diagnostic and
clinical history.
But their limitations is that the
referral does not constitute clinical
clearance.
They're not responsible for determining
medical appropriateness, dosing, safety,
planning or administrative decisions.
And then we would also have a determining
clinician who would be a clinician
operating within their authorized scope
responsible for determining medical
appropriateness for psilocybin treatment.
They would be the ones evaluating
clinical appropriateness for psilocybin
use.
They would review medical history,
mental health history and current
functioning.
They would assess contraindications,
evaluate medication interactions,
assign clinical support tier,
establish dosing parameters or
considerations,
approve or defer participation based on
safety.
So we completely stripped out any
language related to prescriptive
authority,
but what we did was separate it out so
that a referring clinician,
I imagine this as a clinician out in the
field.
They're not primarily involved in
psilocybin,
but they may refer a patient as or use
psilocybin as a tool and their toolbox
for patients may refer a patient out if
they see a patient with qualifying
conditions and they can get the ball
rolling,
but they wouldn't be necessarily
responsible for the actual medical
clearance.
The medical clearance would be a person
primarily working in psilocybin services.
They would be the one to evaluate and
assess patients to ensure the patient is
safe and that there are no foreseeable
adverse events.
So let's I wanna hear the committee's
opinions on the separating out of
clinicians.
So if anyone has any comments, questions,
concerns.
All right, looks like we got Chris first.
Chris, you can unmute when ready.
Yeah, this seems, I mean, I,
I feel like this is an,
another way to include a prescribing
authority in the mix,
which we kind of discussed thoroughly
last week as being unnecessary.
You know,
I'm here to represent the large number of
veterans we have in New Mexico and vast
majority of them rely on the VA to,
for their medical services and that the
medical system is just not going to be
involved in this program or be supportive
of it in, in any way.
And, you know,
I can go talk to my VA doctor and get all
kinds of contraindicated medications in a,
in a very short amount of time.
And so I'm,
I'm not entirely sure that our
traditional or Western medicine system is
the best prepared to make that
determination anyway.
And we see it in Colorado and Oregon.
The facilitators are able to determine
with their training when people need
consultation and do basic screenings.
You know it.
I would like to see something where I get
AI get a diagnosis and it doesn't matter
where that diagnosis comes from,
but that that's an authorization to to
enter this program in some way.
And you know, in Colorado and Oregon,
what they're showing,
it's safe to do so at the lowest levels.
And you know,
this being a medical program,
I don't think that's going to quite
happen.
But but as close as we can get to that,
the better We're adding additional steps
and a more burdensome process that is in
my view unnecessary.
And we can,
we can evaluate patients at a the lower
or participants at a lower level and use
consultation and referrals when necessary.
Thank you.
I do want to clarify,
nowhere in this new document does it
require prescriptive authority at all.
The what it requires is it says if you're
going to let's say a licensed social
worker,
they determine they see you have PTSD,
they can say, oh,
I'll go ahead and refer you.
You can go ahead and go onto your program.
This is a tool in their toolbox.
It's separating out what the clinician is
doing because so that people in the VA or
people in federally regulated industries
can say, OK, I've I'm not a part of this.
I didn't determine medical
appropriateness,
but I deferred it to someone who is going
to work primarily in psilocybin.
Not necessarily a doctor,
not necessarily a nurse or any specific
person.
They're just determining medical
appropriateness for psilocybin treatment.
That way we can ensure that in a medical
program, we're not making people unsafe.
All right, let's see.
Next we've got Kate Hark.
And Kate, your mic is enabled.
You can unmute when ready.
Yeah, thank you.
You know,
given that this is medical and obviously
there has to be someone who can do
prescriptions, and I'm just wondering,
is there going to be, you know,
special training and guidance for those
people?
And then also I'm wondering about,
you know,
people who just basically refer
themselves maybe to their through their
primary care provider.
They don't really need to go find
somebody else if maybe they've informed
themselves enough to be interested.
But then they still need to go through
the system, you know,
to get the evaluation and prescription.
So I'm just wondering how those things
will be handled.
Yeah.
So in this model,
what happens is we recognize that most
traditional clinicians are not properly
trained in psilocybin or psilocybin use.
So what it allows them to do is they can
just say, OK,
you have a qualifying condition,
I'm going to just go ahead and say this
may help, you should check it out.
Then the determining clinician is the one
who actually says this is safe,
that you are.
We looked at your clinical
appropriateness,
we reviewed your medical history,
your mental health history,
you we assessed your contraindications
and all of that part of safety and
actually determine and say, OK,
you're going to be safe in this program.
But it allows a little bit of a gap
between our traditional providers and our,
you know,
psilocybin services so that they are less
scared to use this treatment.
Yeah, that makes sense.
I don't know that I think I still have
the question about what kind of
qualifications or education is going to
be provided to the people who who need to
be knowledgeable.
And then how does that fit with just,
you know,
anybody who could make a regular
prescription,
write a prescription for something else?
Is there going to be another layer of
like they need to be informed or can it
be any, you know, doctor,
other prescriber?
What I was hoping with with this program
was that it would be we would set the
role and then we would defer it to
education and training to set the actual
like curriculum recommendations and what
they need to be taught.
So we've provided the responsibilities,
what they need to be able to do,
and then they will determine the
specifics of, like,
how they're going to be trained on this
material.
Got it.
Yeah, That makes sense.
So what about somebody who just is
interested by whatever they've heard and
they talk to their doctor,
and then what happens if that doctor
isn't, you know, specializing in this?
Would they have to go to another referral
and then back to the doctor or?
So what I would imagine is we would make
it very,
very easy to be a referring clinician.
So that way any provider could just enter
in and be like just say hey,
like go check this out and make sure this
is safe.
But here's like they have a diagnosis.
That way it would hopefully allow most
providers to just register and then they
would be referring clinicians.
And then whoever wanted to be a
determining clinician would have to go
through psilocybin specific training to
understand, you know,
all of the contraindications and
medication interactions and what why
certain medical history is a problem and,
and that kind of thing.
That was what I was imagining,
but I would like to hear what the
committee thinks.
Yeah, I, I think that makes sense.
So really the referring is about well you
qualify on the basis of these diagnosis
and now somebody else will look at it
more closely.
Yes, OK, thank you.
All right.
And I see Chris's hand next and Chris you
can unmute one ready.
Thanks for the clarification, Ian,
and I apologize maybe I jumped to
conclusions there would.
So would somebody be able to do both?
Would somebody be able to do the
referring and the medical clearance in
one step?
I think that would be important for,
you know,
not making bottlenecks in this process.
If they were like a licensed clinician
acting within their scope who already
possesses diagnostic authority, yes,
if could because you don't have to be a
licensed clinician to be a determining
clinician.
You have to be just a person who we are
defining a new role authorized within
their scope for specifically determining
medical appropriateness for psilocybin
treatment.
So they would be trained on all of the
stuff on, you know, like I said,
medical history, contraindications,
medication interactions,
assigning clinical support tiers,
which are a patient interaction,
patient qualification and safety
committee adopted to say you know what
those specific high risk ones are and
that kind of thing.
But no worries, I appreciate all input.
All right,
and next we've got Denali and you can
unmute when ready morning again.
I just wanted to introduce a perspective.
Well, first echo, you know,
the feedback on, you know,
making sure that we're not creating
systems that are so cumbersome that they
may impede equity and access.
I think anytime we introduce a new
clinician or a new step that will have
impact on on equity and access both for
providers in the space and and for
patients.
All of this is always a give and take,
right?
You know,
if we're focusing more on safety,
you know,
that necessarily is going to increase the
regulatory burden or all these things.
So I, I know it's,
it's a delicate balancing act,
but something I'm not sure that we've
talked about at length in this committee
that I think is relevant,
especially as we start putting words to
people's roles and what we're asking them
to do is, is coverage issues.
So, you know, it's a,
it's a really complicated space to be
working within a medically integrated
system.
How,
how do we integrate the components of
this care that are elements of care that
Medicaid and 3rd party payers are already
covering and should continue to cover?
You know,
I think primarily prep and integration as
seen as, as, as,
as reimbursable therapeutic services.
But we,
we cause coverage problems when we,
when we blend those,
those components of care with the aspects
of the,
the program that are not reimbursable,
right,
Anything to do with the administration
day or the actual ingestion of a Schedule
1 substance.
And,
and I'm flagging this because it's also
relevant there.
There's that blending issue.
And also whenever we start talking about
referrals,
there's going to be an issue around
around coverage.
Most third party payer contracts have a
clause that prohibits unauthorized
referral to any unauthorized treatment
modality.
So that means, you know,
if you're providing care and in as a
component of that provision of care,
you are making a referral to an
unauthorized treatment modality of the
Medicaid or third party payer will
decline coverage for that,
for for that care that you received.
And so there's,
there's a tricky line that we have to
walk because, you know,
ensuring that we have as,
as Chris mentioned,
there's a lot of things that are not
great about the existing medical system.
And I think the the pieces that community
is interested in incorporating is the
access component, right.
If we can integrate into the pieces that
provide people with the opportunity to
receive to receive services paid either
through state Medicaid program or through
a third party payer like that just
tremendously improves improves access for
for our communities.
And and so this this line that we have to
walk around referral is,
is important and it's one that's been
walked before.
So you know,
the the recommendation is going to be
that we're not requiring anywhere in
documentation for what people's roles are,
is that they're either required to make a
referral or to assess that psilocybin is
like to recommend psilocybin that carries
other professional liability issues,
but but they have similar implications on
the viability of the program.
I wandered a little bit there,
but wondering if there's anything more
that I can provide at this point.
Yeah.
What would you prefer instead of referral?
So I,
I think the the easiest way to create
compliance and protect for coverage would
be well, here,
let's look at can I look at this again?
All right.
Well, I,
I think the problem is a little bit
deeper,
which is why I'm having having a hard
time responding.
We want people to be able to integrate
within the behavioral like the behavioral
health services that many people are, are,
are already accessing their work with an
individual therapist, you know,
who may be engaging other treatment
modalities that are, are relevant to,
to whatever you know, this person,
this person is seeking care for.
The the thing that we have to protect is
that provider's ability to provide
information about psilocybin that doesn't
constitute A referral.
If if you know,
something rises to the level of a
referral,
then whatever care that they're receiving,
that is, you know, the care that they,
they continue to they're already they're
already receiving it is it's going to be
uninsurable.
So I'm struggling a little bit,
but I might, I might not have a good,
a good solution in the course of the
meeting, but just something to,
to think about.
And we did provide and to the department
a legal memo about insurance and the
phases of care, as, you know,
best defined within a perspective of but,
you know,
preserving ability to to provide coverage.
So maybe it would be helpful for me to
share that as well.
Yeah.
May I just jump in?
This is Robert Trochner, Denali.
I think the term we're playing with now
is the word certify.
You know,
we're not it because this seems to be
what was used in medical cannabis and it
seemed to jump around the edges.
We're we're certainly not set on that
word.
And as you said,
we are playing a game with insurance
where we need to find the correct to
protect not only the provider,
but yet get the patient in the therapy.
And so the word we're dancing around now
is certified.
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks for that perspective.
And I think that that may,
that may work really well.
I think though that the other piece that
I'm struggling with here is right that
the psilocybin Act is different from our
medical cannabis act.
And I think it's been innovative and what
we've learned about that line since
medical cannabis in that right,
the the determination of eligibility is
based solely on diagnostic criteria,
not like medical cannabis where, you know,
there is some medical benefit piece
because we've under we've come to
understand that that that puts providers
at exposes them to to unnecessary risk
with making recommendations to a schedule
one program.
So I think that certifying works and this,
but this question of determination that
really is requiring a a physician to make
A to say that there is some medical
benefit goes both beyond the scope of the
medical psilocybin Act,
which which connects diagnostic like the
the eligibility to participate is based
only on, you know, the,
the presence of a condition.
And then I see you're shaking your head
though, Ian.
So tell me what you're thinking.
The ACT says that they must determine
medical appropriateness as well,
but based on,
but if medical appropriateness is based
on the, the condition itself,
that's because we can't create a program
where we're asking providers to determine
that a,
a federally illegal substance has a
medical benefit.
It, you know,
creates a lot of professional liability
and even federal criminal liability for
our providers.
It looks like you have the the this open,
but maybe we can just read what the full
piece is.
So the medical appropriateness is based
on, right.
So a patient whose clinician has a judge
the patient to be medically appropriate
candidate for the use of medical
psilocybin based on being diagnosed with
a qualifying condition.
I do recognize that,
but it's also says judged.
That's clinical judgment right there.
Yeah,
I maybe I maybe got us a little bit off
track.
I know there are other things,
but certainly an important both the line
of of insurance coverage and professional
liability and other, you know,
protection from criminal liability for
our providers are going to be important
ones to walk both, you know,
considering how those are appropriately
anticipated by the statute and maybe,
you know,
not as effectively as they could be,
right.
All of this is,
is really iterative and it may mean that,
you know, we,
we return to conversations about how best
to to protect folks, right?
And I do think that there is a lot riding
on a qualifying condition.
My concern is more so that qualifying
conditions, many of these come with,
you know, medications to treat them.
Many of them come with other aspects of
having these disorders.
And so I just my primary concern is
patient safety.
And I know that this is not the most
dangerous drug in the world,
so I'm open with being, you know,
less restrictive.
But at the same time with when we did
medical cannabis,
we had them certify that the benefits
outweighed the cons.
When we put medical in front of something,
people are going to assume that that
judgement has been made.
And so it's very unnerving for me to just
completely disregard that section and
just say, hey,
we're only gonna look at the qualifying
condition and nothing else.
That would scare me a little bit.
That's if that's what the committee wants.
I will ultimately subside to the majority.
But I do believe I,
I did work really hard to try to say like
here is there's no prescriptive authority
in this.
There's no like real requirement other
than the certified,
the person who is saying yes,
this is OK has diagnostic authority,
but I will ultimately turn over to James.
He's been waiting a little bit.
All right, James in your mic is enabled.
You can unmute when ready.
Thank you, Ian, everyone.
Great.
Ian, this is right where we needed to go.
I think because of the,
this is almost a very safety,
a very close, narrow sweep.
We're looking at very close definitions
here,
but also we have a very broad categories
of treatment.
You know, we're,
we're talking about people who,
who are going to be clergy to people who
are going to be, you know,
dealing with MDD and trauma.
So I mean,
this is so amazing that you were able to
put this is very close.
And I, I just want to make sure that,
you know,
because we're saying certified clinician
and diagnostic thing and,
and that is right up the alley of
insurance.
Has anybody talked to Medicaid,
New Mexico Medicaid and be in contact
with that group to see how can we with
Denali's question and the billing,
how do we work that out?
You know, have you,
has the DoH been in contact to say, hey,
this has come in what language do we need
to use here?
Was that thought about over?
So from what I know from the department
and I do not speak for the department,
but they were in contact.
And So what I do know is that the like
semantics of what we put in the board
recommendation isn't gonna be the like
legal language and the rule.
So the department will have wide
discretion to shift it to make it
compliant with Medicaid.
But I believe Robert had a point as well.
Yeah, If I can just jump in here.
Yes, yes.
Jeez.
We've been working.
We've had a meeting with Medicaid.
I have reached to outside billing
agencies.
We have Denalis paper that her and
Victoria made.
I'm working with a group called Brain
Futures out of the East Coast.
So yeah,
there's been actually a fair amount of
thought that's gone into this.
We're defining the definitions.
I've written something up that once
Dominic looks like I'd I'd like to
present to Medicaid so we can start
narrowing down how exactly and what
exactly we need to do to get this paid
for as therapy essential.
Thank you.
Great.
And that was right where I was thinking
you guys were already stepping,
which I appreciate that.
And so as we get more of the refined
definitions,
that will be very important for people.
One of those questions was guides is that
are we saying,
Ian here a guide is the facilitator?
I just want to make sure,
is that the thought here?
Thank you.
Yeah.
And the propagation rules,
a guide was how they described A
facilitator.
So that's how I updated this document.
All right,
And next we've got Gregory Evans and Greg.
You can unmute when ready.
Just before I get into my comment here,
the NMACG .1 actually refers to guide.
So I think we are beholden to that
language,
but we get to like determine the
interpretation of what that means, right?
But moving on, lots of stuff.
I put some things in the chat,
a few alternative terms for referral,
just ideas or whatever.
The idea of identification and
identifying clinician could be very
useful in sidestepping the insurance
issues.
So like say I'm,
I go to my PCP and my PCP has knowledge
of the program and that like my normal
annual visit for my checkup and he's
aware of my treatment resistant
depression and he is familiar with my
process with my psychiatrist and my talk
therapist.
But he says, hey, you know what,
I think you might be a good fit for this
program.
That's all.
That's all that person does.
And then says this is a person you can go
to clear your qualifying conditions and
contraindications.
To qualify for treatment resistant
depression,
any type of in any type of context,
you have to have a documented history of
protocols that you've tried to treat
depression with.
So there already has to be a history.
So this person has seen a a prescribing
psychiatrist and how should would have a
history in that story, right?
There's many other stories,
but the idea here is that your chaplain
could be that person that says, hey,
why don't I I've identified you as
somebody who could go into this pipeline.
Let's get you set up with the resources
you need that that person could also be a
Corondera that you've had a long standing
relationship with and they're like, hey,
let's see what the medicals.
Pipeline will do for you,
but like I'm going to stay with you
through this whole process,
but you need to go see this clinician
that has the, you know,
the funny hat that says he can sign a
paper saying that you've tried everything
there is to do to treat your depression
and that the and and so that's going to
be a gate that we have to deal with.
But I don't think if we look at the piece
I put in here for determining clinician,
which would then which could then turn to
identifying the hold on.
Let me find where I was for the readiness
assessment.
That could be psychiatrists.
This,
this is like determining your like that
you have no contraindications,
which is super important for the program.
And then like that you've actually
qualify as one of the four things that we
have.
It's a very narrow scope.
We'll do like this will open, right.
But this could be an LCSW or an LMFT or
your psychiatrist or in your natural path.
If your naturopath is a naturopathic Dr.,
they can say that like if your
acupuncturist actually has a prescribing
degree, that could fit into that bucket.
But then like the the medical clearance,
like get a little bit trickier.
Beyond that,
I think the pipeline of care and we'll
get down to the further definitions.
That's what's really important in making
sure that like where our like more
ambiguous historical practitioners get
contained in the language that we choose
to provide into the recommendation for
what the facilitator and the integration
provider means and what the
qualifications for those are.
And to be clear,
we need to understand that those
qualification parameters like need to
come out of the TNE group,
but we can like crosswalk this
information to them.
I hope that's enough clarity from my end.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I see Rob put his hand up again.
Rob,
did you want to speak to anything in that
specifically?
Yeah, I do,
but there's someone in front of me,
isn't there?
Yeah.
Cool.
Yeah, we'll go to Larry then.
And Larry, I have enabled your mic.
You can introduce yourself and speak.
Winrith.
Yeah, this is a great discussion.
It's really hard to actually sort this
out there until we know what's being
required.
To me, the determining clinician,
I think this would be the case in
Colorado,
is actually someone who's done training
in, in, in, in psychedelic therapy,
whether that's from CIS or a facilitator
program.
I mean, it's not,
it's not a a physician that's like taking
a Saturday afternoon course and doing
this.
And so it's really important to that out
if, if I understand in Colorado,
when someone has a condition such as PTSD
or treatment resistant,
there's an involvement of you can you can
be a dual person, you can be a, you know,
a, a medically trained person.
But I'm,
I'm just curious what people in this
group are thinking the training of this
determining clinician.
This is it 100 hours or is it like,
is it like a weekend course?
I,
I would argue that this is the key role
here in determining, you know,
benefit and safety and that it probably,
and, you know, speaking as a physician,
my colleagues that are doing this have
been doing that level of training.
So I'm,
I'm just don't really want us to sort of
become the first ones to lower the bars
to, you know,
you take a weekend course in psilocybin.
So I'm curious what other people are
thinking.
Thank you.
So in regards to that,
I was actually kind of there with you.
I was there was a comment it says I think
they were talking about the amount of
time slash training at the last training
and education meeting last week.
But you know, I had definitely.
So before we had required someone to be
licensed.
I don't know that it's within our
jurisdiction to define those education
requirements here.
I think it would have to get adopted and
then the education committee would have
to adjust to the adoption.
But we need some sort of referring
framework in the program per the statute.
So I do recognize the importance of
requiring strong education for this
person.
They are have a lot of responsibility on
them.
All right.
And Doctor Truckney.
Yeah, thanks.
I, I'm going to throw out some ideas.
We haven't decided.
I'm not speaking for the Department of
Health.
It's just some things worth thinking
about.
I, I,
I want to pitch a patient flow to you to
get your input.
Let's pretend I'm a patient with
treatment resistant depression.
I'm interested in the program.
I've read about it online.
I go to my regular doc and I say,
you know, what do you think about this?
And the doc and your doc could be your
General practitioner,
it could be a psychiatrist,
it could be your therapist,
it could be any of this group.
And they look at your medical record and
say, well, yeah,
this may actually help you.
I can't officially recommend it.
I can quote certify you or something else.
But then that's the referral in that can
be billed as a regular visit and
borrowing a term from a psychiatrist in
Colorado that I spoke to.
And I, I, I,
we're going to call people medical
psilocybin or mushroom therapists.
So I almost am thinking,
what if this is a therapist driven
program?
A mushroom therapist is a therapist
licensed in the state who has psilocybin
training.
And to Larry's point, not a weekend.
They have the full facilitator slash
guide course.
This person then becomes the centerpiece.
They can assess the patients.
They are aware of the four diagnosis.
They can perform testing if needed to get
a baseline testing.
And then if they find a medical problem,
let's say I have treatment resistant
depression, but I'm hypertensive,
I'm not taking my antihypertensive.
Then they send him back to the medical
doctor to say, hey,
can you fix this hypertension?
And then once the hypertension's fixed,
we got the medical clearance taken care
of.
And then we come back to the quote
mushroom therapist.
And then they, as part of their therapy,
they talk about the prep sessions,
they talk about what psilocybin is,
and then they can quote, certify,
or hand them off to a facilitator or a
guide.
These aren't therapies.
These are facilitators or guides who have
a complete training and then the dosing
day is held by the guys and facilitators.
The patient goes, I go there,
I fill out my paperwork,
I have a great journey,
I have some insight.
The facilitator who is with me is
excellent.
They fill out a HIPAA compliant form,
send it back to my therapist,
and then integration happens back with my
therapist.
What do you guys think about a flow like
that?
Thank you.
I for one loved it,
but I will definitely hear from the rest
of the group.
All right now, Gregory, well put.
I'm a story driven developer,
so I love that.
Thank you, Robert.
To Doctor Lehman's question about the
weekend approval,
I think it's more like you have a
doctorate and you are an expert in your
field and then you go to the weekend
education of, you know, like maybe it's,
it's more than a weekend, but it's like,
there's a certain like the TNE committee
will define what those actual parameters
are for certification, but like,
and what the education models need to
follow to provide that.
But I think you know,
it's like if you are already a high level
doctorate pharmacologist absorbing how
other 5 HC 2 interactions occur and the
specifics of psilocybin are,
are are not super complicated, but we can.
But I think the conversation currently is
going towards a competency level
assessment, right?
Especially with TRD,
we have this we very commonly may need
like the intervention of current drug
protocols that you're on maybe could be
something that slows the process.
Like if you are on an SSRI that needs to
be weaned for six months that like
preparatory.
May be guided very,
very differently than somebody who's
accessing for acute PTSD and is
unmedicated.
But as far as like the flow that Doctor
Truchner just described,
this is kind of like what I've been like
dreaming of in it.
In essence,
it's like you have multiple entry points,
right?
You can find your way into the program
and then the program becomes a flow and
the program has multiple requirements,
but like there are different types of
bodies that can fill those requirements.
And as a patient from a patient centric
flow,
the journey of finding those those
providers that unlock the requirement
from the program to meet the program's
needs is more of a non linear pattern.
Like this is like Doctor Truchter
described a very linear story,
but like there are a lot of those things
are blocks that could be moved around,
right?
Like the example of being kicked back to
deal with hypertension,
Like that's not something that
everybody's going to deal with.
But during that period of, of, of,
of dealing with your hypertension,
you could still be working on preparation
with your therapist.
And like the program does have a specific
therapeutic protocol of,
of advanced preparation,
dosage integration and follow up.
And it's like you could decide that the,
the initial spiritual care provider that
you were going to do dosage with like
doesn't fit somewhere in that protocol or
like somewhere in your prep preparation.
And you've discovered that you might be
aligned with somebody else.
And you can replace those people with,
with mechanisms that might be more
appropriate for you.
But the interesting,
the one question that I have coming out
of that protocol here is how do we,
how do we define who can hand the person
the medicine and what that facilitator is
'cause I really don't see that like the
person,
unless you have like this weirdly
intimate relationship with your
prescribing psychiatrist and he's and
that's the per that is the person that
clears your contraindications.
Like there's no real reason for that
person to be in the room.
But we could have a qualified pharmacist
that is a facilitator that attends a
session with a guide and that guide works
alongside that person in let's try not
let's try not to leverage the word
supervised,
because that will that can kind of
destabilize some of like the hierarchical
inflections.
When we have say you have a 90 year old
kurandera that is performing your guide
work,
but your your physician is the one that's
there to take care of all of that.
Or like your nurse practitioner,
somebody like like James right,
can be there to administer,
hold the space,
the guide is there to work with your
spirits and do all the stuff in there.
And then that team,
someone from that team could be your
integration coach or your integration
coach could attend that session as a
different type of support figure.
But like,
the patient gets to choose how this is
all pieced together and there is a team
of people helping them piece those needs
together.
I hope that's not too verbose,
but I've done way too much thinking on
this.
Thank you.
All right.
And next we've got Chris Peskowski.
And you can unmute when you're ready.
OK, I guess I,
my mind's going up about 100 different
places after that.
But first of all,
I don't like the term guides at all.
I think it's not very culturally
appropriate and disrespectful of
traditional healers and indigenous
cultures that have been holding this
medicine for a long time.
I really prefer the use facilitator for
this work.
And I think it's the most commonly kind
of used term.
And, you know, being a facilitator myself,
like I'm not there to guide somebody in
their process.
I'm there to help them with my presence
and be there with them and to make it
easy.
And that's the root word of facilitator
is facil.
And that's how it was explained to me and
why those people are called that.
So I, I hope that we,
we can minimize the use of guide or maybe
even change that,
but I don't think it's a,
a very culturally appropriate term at all.
Second,
like I really don't think that we need a
physician's assistant or a pharmacist in
the room on dosing day.
Like this is something that can be done
again safely at the lowest level.
And if we limit our facilitators to just
administration day,
I think that's very harmful like this
should they should be involved in the
preparatory work with our our
participants and need to be involved in
that process.
And also, I think, you know,
facilitators that are also peer support
specialists or others can provide a great
deal of support in the integration
process as well.
And, you know,
from an economic standpoint,
I just don't think a facilitator could
make a living just doing dosage sessions.
And I don't think it would be wise either.
I don't think this is a relational work.
And they need to be,
they need to know the participants before
they're sitting in in the medicine with
them.
That's super important.
And, you know,
as a veteran who had to go out of the
country and do this,
I had to kind of figure a lot of this out
on my own, you know,
and facilitation or integration looks a
lot differently for everybody, you know,
And a counsellor would have been a
terrible integration coach for me.
You know,
a lot of my integration comes in the the
martial arts gym and through other
activities that helped me move my energy
in a way that allows me to be my best
self.
So I just hope we can expand what a
facilitator does and how they're involved
in this process.
And I'll,
I know there's a bunch of people that
want to talk,
so I'm going to turn it over.
All right.
And next we've got Larry.
And Larry,
you can unmute when you're ready.
Yeah.
I just want to bring up one question here,
like the,
I think what we're calling now the
mushroom therapist of the physician,
Does that role include being available if
there are issues that come up, you know,
during the therapy?
Like is there an ongoing role for I guess
this is a question of ongoing role of
medical involvement in supervision.
Has that been come up in any discussions?
So I would have imagined them being more
involved.
I'm still like trying to figure out how
to word this because I do think we need
to,
but I don't think that specific
discussion has been had yet.
OK, can I jump really good?
I'm sorry, can I jump in again?
I'm sorry.
I'm jumping line a little bit.
I yeah, you know, my,
the example I gave was kind of the bare
bones example.
So I want to answer both Larry's very
good question and Chris's concepts as
well.
Larry, yes,
the quote the mushroom therapist is the
person who's going to be available
whether or not, you know,
it's a billing thing.
How do we, how do we parse this?
But in general, in my perfect world,
we're going to have the facilitator
during the dosing session.
We're also going to have quote the
mushroom therapist available, right?
There is also another potential way to
bill for this.
And it's really pushing the envelope,
but it's called an acute psychiatric
crisis.
Pitched this to Medicaid and they seemed
a bit dubious,
but we're working on this where the
mushroom therapist who's this licensed
therapist and trained as a facilitator,
they're there.
And once the patient,
let's say the patient struggles during
their journey,
the mushroom therapist can kind of step
in and deescalate if needed.
If that happens,
then potentially you can bill for acute
psychiatric billing codes.
And so that may be a way.
So Larry, there's two things.
One, yes,
I think the mushroom therapist has to be
available, if not in the facility,
has to be very close by.
And two, I, I,
we're working on trying to get that
billed.
Now going back to Chris's point, yes,
Chris, I agree with you 100%.
I didn't go into that level of detail.
I, you know, in this ecosystem,
in my mind,
this may be a therapist driven program.
I think you as an excellent facilitator
will work very closely with the therapist.
And I agree,
you need to be there during the prep
sessions because the person that is
undergoing the journey needs to trust you.
They need to know you.
They need to know your style.
They need to know what to expect.
So yes,
you will be there and I agree with you.
You also need to be present during the
integration sessions.
So you are not, I, you said it perfectly,
you're just not there during the dosing
session.
You have a role both before,
during and after.
The last thing I want to bring up is
administration in this program.
I,
I think we've talked internally about
self administration.
This avoids a lot of legalities and laws.
And you know,
we know from Oregon that they have a
staff member come in with a silver tray,
blueberries and chocolate,
and they give him their mushroom and the
patient takes their mushroom off the tray
and self administers.
I think self administration for billing
and liability issues is going to be huge.
So I think we need to think about it that
way.
And I agree with Chris that, you know,
Chris,
I you don't need to have anybody else
present.
That just complicates it.
Thank you.
All right, all right,
It looks like I'm next.
Thank you.
This is Jorge.
I just want to say like this is where we
need to be and I appreciate these
conversations because this is exactly
where we need to be defining these roles.
Thank you, Ian, and for all folks present,
thank you for your input because this is,
this could be really challenging and,
and it's part of the process.
And this is a fruitful discussion that
needs to be had because there are so many
committee,
so many folks who are who are taking part
in this and, and across committees.
And there are different terms being used
in definitions and,
and even to what Chris said about,
you know,
we want to be culturally appropriate and
considerate in the language that we use.
And, and so I that,
that's important because we'd also don't
want to get roles confused either because
that can be confusing for folks across
committees and,
and committee members and chairs around
the language or speaking.
So with that, I,
I think I believe it's really important
that we always go back to what's in the
statute because that's what we have as a
basis.
So the statute just defines clinician and
and I see that's what Ian has put up here
and then and a patient as well.
So,
but also we we're looking at what's
what's been published,
the producer and laboratory roles,
those are open for public discussion at
this point and public comment and April
24th as a reminder,
that's when we have the hybrid public
hearing as well.
April 24th, 9:00 to 12:00.
And I'll put that information later on in
the chat.
But if you look at those definitions,
those definitions are still growing and,
and which means is that as we go into
training and education,
those folks in that committee can also
add to those definitions.
And so they're going to the point of, of,
of, of what a guide is or a facilitator,
right?
Those definitions seem to be very similar
of what people are using.
And So what that says, I just,
I just want to read that an individual
has completed training and education
approved by the department to be able to
assist practitioners during the
administration sessions and who has been
registered with the department.
And then if we look at practitioner,
this means an individual who is licensed
healthcare professional,
who is certified by the Department of
Fried Medical Psilocybin Integrative
Therapy,
supervise the guides and who has
completed department required training.
So in essence,
a person could actually be the clinician
and the practitioner or even all three as
a guide facilitator.
So people had asked those questions.
Can people do this one?
And that one's like, yeah,
and he even brought that up.
And yes, if they, if they fall within,
within their role and, and,
and scope of practice, absolutely.
So I, I hope this helps a little bit also,
but thank you for this,
this conversation and reminding.
Yeah, this can,
this can be frustrating and, and,
and confusing at times,
but it's also part of the process.
And I'm and I'm glad we're,
we're at this point working on this so
that as we move forward,
it becomes clearer to folks.
So again,
just a reminder to go back to the statute
and to the rules and those rules can also,
you know,
as far as the definition can be changed
as we move along as well.
Thank you.
And James, you know,
back to Chris's point and my my point
earlier with that guide definition,
I think just again,
we just need to be careful on what we're
gonna define certain terms on to make
sure that again, it cross pollinates.
I do like the docs idea of a pathway,
you know,
to make sure that we're getting these
people the right person at the right time.
And again,
guides are more of we're sitters.
You know, what's the real job of a guide?
It's the sit.
And so that's really the,
the thought behind guides or even
facilitators.
It's their space, it's their container,
it's their growth, it's their healing.
And so, yeah, we're going to be there,
but we're really going to be there for
them to just to support them in that time
and effort.
And I do like the effort of,
of just to give you guys an idea of what
we're trying to do in our program is just
to allow people, the facilitator,
the practitioner,
all of us meet at different times with
the individual that's going to go through.
And it's different than Oregon.
And Oregon, again, we focus on self.
A lot of those people self journeying.
If you look at the data,
it's all self journeys.
And so if we look at that and we,
and we have to kind of apply this to a
different model.
And so that's the thought process here is
how do we let people go through the self
and in that container, but also that it,
it focuses back on integration.
And so as we do these pathways,
integration and therapy is the key.
Like you guys brought up earlier,
it's a great point.
These are the people who are going to be
driving this program is to make change,
but also we're going to have people that
go through the end of life and then other
additions as we go through that,
we got to think about that too.
So it's a some of these are broader
sweeps versus an arrow.
And so again,
I like the idea of of having the
facilitator or guide,
whatever we term it as being there before
session,
at least what I would call a minimum.
Ian,
we want to look at minimums here or not
to overburden the process.
Just thoughts.
Thank you.
All right.
And let's see.
We will go to Chris next.
And Chris,
you can unmute when you're ready.
Yeah, I, I think I wanted to come back.
I, I appreciate your clarification, Dr.
Chuckner, but I also, you know, in,
in an ideal world, I,
I think we're doing this in groups with
multidisciplinary teams kind of presence
and all working with the,
the participants and working together.
But often times people need to do some
individual work before they do group work.
And I don't necessarily think that two
people need to be in the room.
We don't need a,
a facilitator and A and a therapist there.
That would increase costs.
And I'm wondering if we might adopt A
system kind of how, you know,
a nurse practitioner,
physician's assistant,
work under supervision of assist of a,
you know, physician.
So you're,
you're in constant consultation and and
supervision with that clinician,
but they're not always necessarily
working directly with the the
participants during that time.
Yeah, thank you.
Awesome.
Thanks, Chris.
And let's see, I see Rob's hand up.
Yeah, Chris, again, very good points.
Thank you.
Yeah, again, this is a complex system.
I think one thing I want to start off
with is we have very,
we have 4 very different medical
conditions,
all require very different levels of
support.
End of life is very different than PTSD.
So as we think about these things moving
forward,
I would love input as we start to get
some fine detail.
I, you know,
different of these medical conditions
require different levels of support and
we have to think about that second thing.
Chris.
Yeah, I, I don't, I,
I didn't mean that there has to be
necessarily two people in the room.
And I agree with you that people don't
jump into group sessions until they've
had some solo sessions.
And you know,
the group dynamics and staffing are very
different than a solo session.
I think my idea of I'm going to use the
mushroom therapist, again,
not being derogatory,
is that they they can be present,
they can be in the building and they
won't necessarily have to be in the room
unless there's maybe a need for them to
be in the room.
Hopefully that that makes more sense to
you, Chris.
Thank you.
All right.
And Larry, I,
I think we need to separate some of these
terms here.
I just don't think they're appropriate.
Like mushroom therapist is talking about
a clinician clinical provider,
they're reviewing medical reconciliation.
That's not a therapist.
Like for instance,
in our studies we have PhD psychologists
that they always have a clinician
involved.
So I think it's almost like we need a
psychedelic trained clinician is actually
some of the term there.
And then maybe psychedel therapist.
I feel like this mushroom therapist is
describing 2 different roles.
I'd call it a psychedelic trained
clinician myself, right?
Do you have anything to add to that Ian
or respond?
I just updated it to psychedelic trained
condition.
I clinician.
I personally have no preference for like
specific titles.
So whatever people are feeling, Robert,
far better word Larry, far better word.
Will you say more about this?
I, I, cuz I'm, I, I'm thinking in,
in my mind,
we can have a PhD psychologist,
we can have a licensed social worker,
anybody who can do therapy as as part of
driving this,
they may not have the ability for medical
clearance on.
So that's why one of my thoughts was like,
well,
if there's questions about medicines and
drug interactions,
we send them back to their physician for
kind of that.
Will you say more about what you're
talking about?
Is that a question for me, Larry?
Absolutely, yeah.
So if if you scroll back up a little bit
here,
we we can't say that you're sending them
back up to the referring physician
because that referring physician doesn't
need to know anymore the certifying.
They just know that they have PTSD or
depression.
They don't really know anything about
psychedelics.
And so I think that the psychedelic
trained clinician role is the one that's
familiar with psychedelics and and
medical medical roles.
So I, I think there's actually, and,
and these roles can overlap,
but I almost see certifying clinician,
psychedelic trained clinician psychedelic
therapist as, as actually different,
different roles.
I would say that no,
like PhD psychologists do not often do
medical reconciliation or review medical
records.
They may sometimes,
but that's not a common role.
That's a clinician role, right?
I think under this model,
kind of what we had imagined was that
psychedelic trained clinician would be
specially so like to be a certifying
clinician, you, you're right.
You just have to know that they have PTSD
or treatment or whatever.
But for a psychedelic trained clinician,
I was imagining sparked significantly
more education and training specifically
to fill in those gaps on assessment or
medication interactions to kind of see
that out.
But I don't.
So how are you imagining it?
So is it certifying?
Then you go to a trained clinician,
then you go to a therapist or I I think
they could potentially overlap.
So psychedelic claim trained clinician
can also be a therapist and it can also
be the one that's doing doing the session.
But I think in some places here,
this said there'd be the psychedelic
trained clinician and then the next,
the next role is the gets into a
therapist facilitator role.
I think that, I think that I, I,
I know it's tempting to,
to want to have like 1 role that
describes it all, but I think it,
it ultimately there may be multiple
models depending on how they're entering
the system.
The bottom line is like the these things
like medical reconciliation,
contraindication,
a lot of those I think are clinician role,
not a, not a therapist role.
Our,
our PhD of psychologists that we work
with the UNM who are, you know, would not,
would not take on that role.
They would refer to the clinician,
which could be a physician or APNP or
such.
Interesting.
So then we're back at the original issue
of do we require the certifying clinician
to have prescriptive authority That would
then require at least the clinician to
get on board and certify.
But the cause of that is they may not be
specifically psychedelically trained if
they are just kind of that outskirts
recommendation enter to with the program.
But Robert, yeah, I,
I still would view the, you know, the,
I'm going to call the physician kind of,
I,
I think the clinician trained in my role
or as Larry said, a nurse practitioner or,
or whoever is more,
the patient's going to come to me and I'm
going to say, well,
you're on these meds and this meds and,
you know, I,
I'm worried a little bit about this.
You know,
I'm designing for a perfect world.
Let's take a step back in the perfect
world.
I'm going to put CME out there for every
provider to take four or five hours if
they are interested to learn about
psilocybin.
So if you go to your primary care
practitioner, they're going to have,
they're not going to do it.
They're not going to know a lot,
but they're going to understand the the
pharmacology of it and they're going to
work on controlling your hypertension.
They're going to make sure your SSRIs are,
are,
are there and they don't have to know
much more about it than that.
And then they can say you are medically
stable.
I mean,
this happens in the medical world when
you go to surgery,
they often call it an internal,
an internal medicine doc to make sure
you're stable for the surgery that's
going to follow.
I think there's a similar analogy here.
Yeah, I think that's all I have right now.
Thank you.
All right.
And Gregory,
you can unmute when you're ready.
Just to footnote,
what was just said is that person will
need to understand the parameters of the
program and that needs to like.
So that training and qualification has to
happen.
It's not like,
it's just like I'm this type of person
and then I have this qualification,
I'm able to do that.
And if you have a system like a like that
has a list in search and alignment logic
to put patients in touch with the correct
people for their program path, then that.
Alleviate some of that lost ambiguity.
You could have somebody like I forget how
to say your name, Solaidwin Urea Dr.
Urea Solaidwin who's like an Agua healer
that has PhD level psychology degree and
the body of her work is making meaning
across cultural frameworks like that.
One person can fill all of the roles
aside from deciding contraindications and
dosage.
But I did see.
I just wanted to see.
I saw Gina with her hand up,
but I'm not sure if they're having
connection issues.
I wanted to hear what they had to say,
if they're still here.
Yeah, Gina, let's see.
OK.
Yeah,
there's your hand and your mic is enabled.
You can unmute when you're ready.
OK.
Yeah.
And I think, yeah,
I remember you were having issues earlier.
Let's see another thing.
If you want, I can drop the,
there's like a phone number we could call
as well.
Let's see.
OK, so she dropped something in the chat.
Still can't unmute.
And I unfortunately need to jump off in a
moment.
Could one of the facilitators please
bring to the conversation that concern
about the location for treatment?
There has been mention of a team member
being in the building in case they're
needed.
This treatment should be recognized as
not being about a medication.
It is a psycho spiritual process.
Creating a psycho spiritually safe
environment would prohibit this work from
happening in any clinical setting.
OK.
And I see Rob's hand up.
Yeah, Sorry, Gina.
It was a short.
It was shorthand.
We are definitely thinking about what
type of facilities.
I don't think I'm speaking out of school
and saying we don't like the Oregon and
Colorado model where you have to be in a
certain building at a certain time.
I agree with you one 100%.
It is set and setting is important.
And we have been asking a lot of
questions about what is appropriate set
and setting not only for PTSD but does it
vary for end of life.
So we're having a lot of discussions
about that.
So thank you for bringing that point up.
The other thing I, I,
I want to bring up two things for
consideration as well.
I, I,
I am working under the assumption in this
state that to Larry's point that we don't
have as many pH DS psychologists as UNM
does.
And so we, I,
I am working under the assumption that
the level of training out there to do all
these things may not exist as much.
And to go back to Denali's question,
you know,
I don't want to throw too many barriers
for equity and access as well.
So that's something to think about.
And,
and then I'm going to raise something
that's very thorny for me.
And, and if you guys can solve it,
I will be thrilled in, in my mind,
there can be a misuse to this system as
well,
meaning that if the bar to entry is too
low and I'm thinking of cannabis mills,
right?
And we know there are healthcare
providers out there who run cannabis
mills.
You just walk in and, and you get,
you get certified.
How do we prevent that from occurring in
this program as well?
I'd be very open to ideas about that.
Thank you.
Unfortunately, I do not have a solution.
That has been a problem since prescribers
have existed,
since they've been the gatekeepers.
So it's an unfortunate side effect,
but Chris had a comment.
Yeah, Chris, you can unmute when you're.
Yeah,
I think I was just going to mention that,
you know,
unlike cannabis where people are,
you know, once they got that,
they're able to go home and just use it
at will.
I think it'll minimize some of that
because this is going to require work
with trained professionals and even doing
the session.
It can't be misused in a recreational way
under under supervision,
and I think that'll eliminate itself.
But I could be wrong.
But my sense is that having the steps and
the preparation and the integration are
required is is going to minimize some of
that already just because we have a bare
minimum of work to do around the journey
session itself.
So that's my thought.
All right.
And Greg, I love that concept.
I have often reflected on the strip mall
doctors,
which is where I got my first cannabis
prescription, you know,
But I think what we have here is,
is twofold.
We have the training and education gate
and then we have research and continuous
improvement.
So between those two inside education,
if we can,
we can build a system that builds the
people that we need.
That's not going to get us to where we
need in December.
But if we can layer in peer attestation
for pre regulatory practitioners like we
have someone, I mean I'll just throw out,
there's several people in this room that
can that could raise their hand and have
100 people stand up for them.
I think that qualifies them.
It doesn't certify them through the
program for the education requirements.
They may have to also jump through a
layer of like showing that they can like
there there has to be some sort of like
gait, right.
But like, let's not hold these.
They don't need to go to one-on-one
psychedelics.
They can teach that class beyond and
there's like there's a lot of interesting
layers inside training and education and
we'll have those conversations all summer.
But when we take it over to research and
continuous improvement,
we have this feedback loop what we can
understand about efficacy from the the
multitudes of data.
If so,
we can have like patient has starts with
this qualifying condition,
goes through this path of preparation,
has these complications clears that has a
session.
These are the people involved.
This is the exact dosage,
this is the chemical analysis of that
specific batch that they're dosed with.
And then this is their integration
outcomes,
this is their follow up outcomes and we
track those 436 three to six months,
one year, five years, whatever.
Over time we can define efficacy of
modality specific practitioners.
We'll see efficacy arise in certain areas
and efficacy not being as stable in other
areas and we can start to learn from that.
And again,
that's not something that we'll have on
day one,
but some of that like here's the people
that have been doing this right.
Here's the people that will stand up for
those people like layering that into our
education model.
And I don't believe we're going to get to
any of the lower definitions today,
such as facilitator and integration
provider,
But like when we start to define those
things like building space in the
language to allow for the education
component of this process to define the
structure for those people.
Is is something that like right now,
as we sit in this meeting today,
is something that like brings me
hesitancy that we shouldn't rush,
that we should continue these
conversations and really just like
understand what the effect of the words
that we're writing today will have.
Awesome.
Thanks, Gregory.
And we will move to James Brown.
Ian on the psychedelically trained
clinician down here.
On scope,
is there anything that we need even on
the definition about,
I know it kind of says harm reduction,
it does say risk stratification,
but is there anything that needs to be
added about harm reduction in the
definition?
Because we do focus that the literature
focuses that on harm reduction and then
safety plan.
Is there anything in that scope that
needs to or responsibility that has to be
develop a safety plan?
I know it kind of talks a little bit
about safety,
ensuring patient safety throughout
assessment,
but you really have to have a safety plan
in place, you know,
and I think that's the the train
clinician needs to make sure that they've
done that to for their scope.
Thank you so much.
And then I went ahead and added the so it
now says evaluate risk for adverse
psychological or physiological response
and develop a safety plan.
And I also added that harm reduction is
in their scope.
All right.
And Rob.
Yeah, Hi.
I would like to ask for some education
too about this.
This isn't another idea I'm gonna throw
out.
And I have I I just don't know enough
about it.
I was talking to another therapist and,
and they wondered if as some type of bar
to prevent.
And you know,
going back to Chris's comment,
you're right,
it's not going to be a cannabis mill,
but I,
I wonder if they brought up the idea of
testing, psychological testing.
So,
and I understand it requires some
education perhaps to be in to do the
psychological testing.
And I, I am asking for help.
Is that true?
Who has that?
And is that a way,
is that something we could require
without and adding too much of A burden?
And should it be required?
Thanks.
All right.
And we'll go to Kate Hawk,
and you can unmute when ready.
Yeah,
I really appreciate the balance of moving
ahead.
And you're doing an amazing job of
keeping us focused and moving.
And I also appreciate that things are
slowing down enough to really think
through these important points so that we
end up with, you know,
something that's going to hold up and
work well.
There's there.
I'm aware that there are a lot of
conversations going on outside of the
system of the official system.
And I know everything that, you know,
becomes part of the regulation needs to
go through the, you know,
the committees and the 30 day public
comment and then finally to the board.
And then, you know,
make sure it all aligns and, you know,
to inform all of these conversations that,
you know, people are getting together.
Santa Fe Psychedelic Society meets next
week.
There's meetings over over breakfasts and
dinners.
And on the on the side,
I just want to mention that there was a
document Gregory actually put together a
very thorough document posted to a chat
group that we have here that kind of
overlaps with some of the things we're
talking about today.
You know,
there's certain things in this document
that are, are different and specified,
and then there's things in the other one
that are good food for thought.
So I'm wondering,
how do we is there a way to feed a
document like that into the system for
people to have access to?
Yes.
So it's going to be medical.
psilocybin@doh.nm.gov.
Johnny,
if you can post that in the chat because
I, I,
I have it here in front of me and now I
will post that in just a second.
Perfect.
But if you send any,
anything to that e-mail,
and if you include in the subject what
committee it's for,
then it'll go to the chair,
who will then use it at the committee.
Or especially like something like this,
where we've kind of gone through a few
iterations.
And realistically,
I don't think we're gonna adopt anything
today.
I think I'm gonna once again,
rewatch the video, check in on it, see,
you know,
what were people actually saying and try
to get as close as I can.
Again,
this was largely based off of James Brown,
so thank you to him.
But yeah,
definitely working with what Rob has said
and what all of you have said,
I believe there is a better version of
this out there.
But I will turn over to Gregory.
I may have made a document.
I can post a link into it here and I can
print it out.
But it is kind of a working document like
I like,
kind of like everything else is going on.
I just keep everything kind of
categorized and and moving,
but I did want to share some of that
stuff to especially like the training and
education crosswalk from our needs and
stuff like that.
And looking at the downstream impacts and
some of the pre regulation pathways
toward people that were taking the like
building.
This worked.
But what I did want to say here was just
in response to your comment about
contribute or the safety plan,
develop a safety plan.
I'd really think that we need to make
sure that the safety plan is contributed
to by all.
And that safety plan can start with the
core therapist,
it can start with whomever,
it could start from this the prescriber.
But I think that just like in like a
doula prepares a birthing plan,
like the person who's carrying that
person through the entirety of the
process should be the kind of origin
point.
And they could,
they could let go of their like domain on
that at a certain point,
But I don't think that it should be
constrained to the psychedelic clinician.
I do think that they should be involved,
but I think that we need to create an
environment where everybody's
communicating and trading information and
the building a system to allow for that
with ease, right?
So like building a system that like
doesn't make it hard to do all this stuff
is super, super important.
And I know that there's pieces in the
works around behind the scenes and around
that.
We'll see emerge,
but I I really believe that we can create
a non linear path for a patient that is
patient centric that gets them through
this pipeline towards healing and that
person's healing being the focus, right?
And all of the cogs around that are just
like little LS chipping away help being
stewards for healing.
I'll stop rambling,
but I if it if I have consent,
I'll post a link to what I what I built.
Sure.
Yeah, yeah.
And if you could actually you can do that
if you could also still e-mail like the
actual document to the file some.
So sometimes like public links for some
of like DoH locations and say locations
just depending on the firewall,
like we can't get to the links.
So if you could do both,
that would be awesome.
I can definitely do that.
The PDF export from the program that I
use is pretty underwhelming.
But all the information will be there.
But it needs to be like a,
it's time stamped and it's like this is
where it'll,
it says this is a working document.
This is requesting input and I would love
to hear back from people on what it says.
Thanks.
Thanks for that, Greg.
And as a reminder,
and as you already know, but other folks,
yeah,
please limit any submissions to the
medical dotsil assignment at TOHN m.gov.
If you have public comments,
please limit that to 3 pages.
I put that in the chat because sometimes
we get lengthy documents and, and,
and that is lot for our chairs to reach
because at some point they received
hundreds and, and thousands of pages.
And,
and that would be helpful to because they
do have their other lives and Ian has a
lot.
Well, I OK, so just on that note,
like I've stopped sending documents in
and this is something that I worked 12 to
15 hours on.
It's 15 pages,
but it's comprehensive and it's well
thought out and every word matters.
But like,
I understand the impact of what you're up
against,
but I don't personally have the time to
cut this down to 3 pages.
I would love an editor to do that for me,
but I'm, I'm,
I'm working 20 plus hours a week on
contributing to this department that
chose not to hire me,
chose not to have me on the board.
And I'm still doing this work.
So I'm not going to edit it down.
And I don't mean to sound curt,
but I need to create a boundary.
Yeah.
Greg, this is Rob.
I,
I would like to read your documents so
perhaps we can make an an exception.
And the stuff you do send,
even from the other committee,
is blocked by our firewall.
So we'll need to have it sent in via
different ways.
Absolutely.
I'd love to send things.
I'd love to share information.
All ready.
Is there any more discussion to be had?
All right,
to give us time to analyze the document
that has been sent to update the
documents for review.
Should we come back and meet at on the
27th?
Sorry, I'm just pulling up calendar now.
Let's see.
OK, the 27th at 9:00, it looks great.
Perfect.
All right.
Any objections to that from any of the
committee members?
Perfect.
Well,
I thank you all so much for being here.
Thank you for taking time out of your
morning and investing your knowledge into
the program to make it better.
We do appreciate all of you that have
come and thank you so much.